all right greetings thank you everyone
for joining we're in our second
discussion on chapter
four let's just jump to it um anyone can
write a question in the chat or raise
their hand or just like unmute and go
for it and it could be like anything you
remember from the chapter or like a part
you liked or we're curious about or just
any any question that you want to jump
in with
like any any section that people prefer
just un unmute just any page any section
oh Aon go for it so all um I I was
really scratching my head trying to
compare figure 44 with figure
46 um there's like
a very large amount of overlap between
the two sets of diagrams but there's
like some very uh so I feel like there's
like a clear parallel setup um there's
some edges that are different between
the two and I was like trying to
understand like what do those changes
mean um and like right these were yeah
uh and in both cases I think especially
the left hand side diagram is like
virtually
identical um between 44 and 46 I think I
have the numbering that right um but uh
yeah I I don't know if that's like too
much to fit into a question but I was I
I thought the difference there must be
meaningful but I I didn't fully I
couldn't make sense of
it it's a great question like for sure
on first pass it's like two cities like
maybe there's some differences and which
roads and what's connected to what but
at a first pass like they are both very
very similar um
so a few things are being shown here um
to to kind of give context on this qu
question let's pull back to figure 43 so
here we see this kind of like Rosetta
Stone figure with a basian graph for the
discrete time model and a basian graph
for the continuous time model on the
bottom they're kind of being like laid
out like this to emphasize their
structural similarity even though
they're treating time differently which
we can return to but the top is treating
variables in terms of discrete sequences
of events whereas The Continuous time is
treating it in terms of higher and
higher derivatives of a given um
variable X the important thing though
that makes these similar other than
their structure is that in a base graph
you have edges are variables and then
the uh I'm sorry nodes are variables and
the edges are causal connections okay so
now we get to aasian message passing
scheme so one of the really cool things
about AAS graph is because the edges
represent the sparsity of causal
Connections in the model you only need
to consider edges that are local to a
node so it's like the traffic at a node
is strictly and entirely defined by the
edges leading in um so when constructing
a given basian model like you specify
the kind of causal architecture of the
world and then messages are passed
between the variables so this is going
to be a slightly different base graph
than the figure
4.3 but it's going to emphasize how
certain kinds of architectures pass
certain messages to each other and then
how that enables different kinds of
computations to happen like there's a
different variable here so like right
off the bat even though we see some
variables that were in figure 4.3 like
pi and S there's also different
variables like the um Epsilon and the
the ITA um okay
so two things are being highlighted in
this figure
4.4 on the left is going to be about
hierarchy and
nesting on the right is going to be
about unfolding Dynamics through time so
the motif on the left that describes the
nesting is going to be like each unit of
four is kind of like a level in a nested
hierarchical model and basically what's
happening is the E is calculating an
error like Epsilon for error and then
those errors are being passed up to a
higher order in the um graphs so that is
like the kind of classical predictive
processing architecture we have strictly
stacked levels and then what's happening
within each level is it's doing a
differencing and then passing the errors
up that's the hierarchical
motif The dynamical Motif is going
through time so this one actually has
more similarity to the discrete time in
4.3 and here it's kind of like a
predictive processing but emphasizing
the dynamic
here's the sequence of observations
coming in current time step the future
time step past time step and then each
of those observations are kind of
meeting in the middle and calculating an
Epsilon based upon the Collision of the
incoming observation and then the hidden
State prediction so like the Epsilon
would be zero if the hidden State
prediction was exactly what the
observation was and then those are
getting passed on
up I'm
um
okay then
4.6 here the only difference is that the
again the very similar shapes with like
the motif of four and the passing up but
now we're in the continuous time setting
so that's why there's um more variables
like we see in the continuous time
World um
and now rather than
representing the past present and future
time
step just like the top here past present
and future time step in
4.6 now they are
representing different orders of the
generalized ordinates of motion so the
first the second and the third
derivatives so 4.4 and 4.6 are kind of
like transposed from figure 4.3 the top
and the bottom but now it's representing
each of those halves in terms of the
message passing that it reflects
computationally so what's cool about it
is it shows again a deeper similarity
between these two kinds of models what's
kind of challenging about it is it's
introducing new
notation and it's not exactly the same
model as
before
any thoughts on that or more more on
that question or it could be a different
question that anyone
has
we can go to any any part of
four or like any any can just anyone can
just unmute and go for it or write in
the chat yes
TCC
it's kind of like Parallax in Vision
like chapter 4 is presenting the
generative models of active inference so
in terms of where we are in the textbook
like chapter one introduced it chapter
one two and three approached active
inference from the low road and high
road and then chapter four is like
actually the kernel of active inference
and then the discreet and the continuous
time are going to be unpacked more in
chapter seven for the discreet and
chapter eight for the continuous time
however here they're being really like
tightly jux opposed and
interwoven again that speaks to a really
deep point which is that time can be
handled either in discreet or continuous
fashion in active inference that's cool
deep Point what's challenging is that
even when they're discussing similar
kind of cognitive functionalities the
notation is very different between the
two
forms it would be confusing in a
different way if the exact same notation
was used because it wouldn't be clear
whether we were talking about the
discreete or the continuous time however
this is kind of like a second set of
vocabulary but we couldn't use exactly
the same because some of the variables
are slightly different but like using Y
for observations in the continuous time
and then using uh o for observations in
discreet
time that's just how they do it in this
chapter so it's kind of like they're
introducing both time
treatments and emphasizing again and
again and again that that both of these
are like two flavors and then they are
going to revisit it in the dedicated
chapter seven and chapter
8 but it's kind of like a double
barreled chapter because they're
introducing generative model not in
terms of like well here's a simpler
generative model now we're going to go
to more complex they're introducing like
a dual stream like the two simplest
forms but anyone can just unmute and go
for it or we can look at the chapter 4
questions or whatever people
prefer okay if no one else has I'll go
again I I'm confused also about the the
structure of um uh policy variables like
okay so like a in a hidden State an
observed State whatever like I can like
sort of acknowledge those are sort of
like things that exist in like some not
fully specified space um policy
especially because I think it's like
trying to call back to reinforcement
learning literature like I feel like in
some what's what's like the type of that
like if you were to describe like the
space in which a policy either the
discret version the pi or the uh
continuous version The V like what that
lives in uh or if you were to like
implement it in a program like what what
the type associated with that is like
what's it shape great question
Pi is a list of all policies so it's
always a vector and it always sums up to
one and that's really the critical move
that allows us to talk about the
likelihood of a policy that's why habit
is the prior on policy and then expected
free energy updates our prior on policy
into a posterior because the shape of
that variable is a list that sums to one
so it's a probability
distribution so affordances are the
actions that can be taken in a moment so
if we're like in a grid world the
affordances will be like up down left
right stay so it'll be like
five then if we're only a single time
Horizon a single time step agents
affordances are the same as policy space
because we're only selecting the next
action so say we have five options if we
had an even prior across those five it'd
be like 0. 2 point2 point2 to and then
that could be sampled from or updated
into a policy
posterior if we're talking about an
agent that does planning then the shape
of Pi is affordances raised to the power
of the time steps so if we have five
affordances and then we're doing two
time steps then Pi is 25 long it's up up
up down up right and so it's all of the
two-way combinations so that's the kind
of
exponential explosion with policy
planning which we can come back to but
at a first pass the important things
about Pi are that it's a list it sums to
one which is what makes it a probability
distribution and it's a distribution
over policies that the agent is
selecting
from just just to clarify or check my
understanding so um then whenever we see
like uh V with the Tilda representing a
trajectory over policies like that is
maybe should be regarded as something
that's like because as exponential and
like a unbounded number of steps is like
not something that we should consider
like concretely representable in a
program interesting so the The
Continuous time setting doesn't do
explicit
planning it does so the the PDP at the
top here this is where we have the kind
of classical computer science
exponential tree search like more and
more discrete combinations you know if
you had five times steps deep you'd have
five to the fifth discrete options it's
kind of like a chess
algorithm um in the continuous time
setting planning is not explicit like
let's just say that we had some wild
function that we were trying to
approximate
when doing this kind of a tailor series
approximation like evaluate the the
function at zero and then take the first
derivative so let's just say we stopped
there we're just going to evaluate the
function and then look at the local
slope that already expands to
everywhere that doesn't mean it's going
to be accurate everywhere but basically
the tailor series does expand no matter
how many levels deep you go it already
implicitly
includes basically infinite future
planning but for explicit planning in a
tree like setting that's where the
discrete time comes into
play in
um in this page um Thomas P's
discussion so early implementations were
in The Continuous State space because
this has the most similarity with like
basian filtering
approaches then people started wondering
well how do we get sequential
Dynamics then they moved into this kind
of coupled dynamical systems space but
then that was only getting so far
because there wasn't an explicit
representation of
planning then they moved into the
discrete planning
environments those branches kind of came
back together by nesting The Continuous
Dynamics at the lower level with the
discrete Dynamics at a higher level so
you could do a lot of work in the
continuous
bace and then also have that like
wrapped by a discrete planning
step that's like a little bit about how
the timeline worked but just to
summarize in the discrete setting this
is the most like classical
planning in the continuous setting you
don't have planning as such it's kind of
like you have a car going around a turn
in the discret um Step uh discret time
world it's trying to estimate all the
branching paths it could take in the
continuous time world the driver's like
I'm turning 20 degrees to the
left that's like the first derivative of
my turning angle and then I'm just I'm
holding to that and then that curve
continues so it's not
explicitly saying at seven times St now
here's where I expect to be so it's the
strength and the weakness of the
discrete time the weakness is that
there's a exponential explosion of the
tree just like a chess algorithm but the
strength is that you can actually talk
about the difference between up up up up
up down and up up up up up right which
you couldn't really get
except by going super deep in the
continuous
space so they both have these kind of
like strengths and weaknesses and then
that is resolved or addressed by
building hierarchical nested models that
have components that have continuous
treatment of time and components with
discreete
time
good call um let's see
in page
73 yes someone else has already added
this but yes good call there's several
typos in the
book
we can go to any of the written
questions or like just any any remark
about how anything that we've gotten up
to or just like anything anything active
related we can totally go for it because
chapter four is just it's kind of like
the heart of active inference
um albeit described in a very um
notational
way David or anyone go for
it uh yeah I was just wondering uh if
there's any relationship to the partial
gamma function in regards to how the
branching um seems to work and fit
backwards like if you're mapping back up
through the stack of the decision tree
that Maps back to the initial I just
didn't see any of the the math there in
the chapter but I've seen some
correlation in some of the um the math
that I've been working on
recently um so if you go further down uh
there's a section on
branching
and the relation yeah so Behavior near
Branch point and the relation between
the branches so I was just wondering if
um if that fits in or if my intuition on
the the correlation is incorrect
there it's an interesting connection I
don't know about like this analytic
family but a few thoughts are inactive
inference we're treating every moments
as a branch point so that is the
control decision slash question is the
branch point is defined by the
affordances that can be taken at that
point and so there's some um you know
there's some kayaking down the river
where no matter which way you Branch
it's like you're going to get kind of
brought back in so like the long-term
consequences don't matter but then
there's other moments where to to go a
little bit one way or the other is going
to
diverge so that is kind of like you have
the agents on the kayak and they have
the behavioral Branch point but of
course just knowing that they can tilt
left or right doesn't tell you about
like the river which is kind of like the
actual process
unfolding so I'm not sure exactly how
that would connect but action is a
branch
point
another another possible connection
there is like in this chapter we're
seeing like the basic kernel like the
minimal essential model that describes
um either you know in either of these
time treatments but then there's all
kinds of other cognitive functionalities
like what's known a sophisticated Act of
inference is where in the moment you're
not just planning um or or trying to
estimate like what will I be doing and
what will I see but you can
also project out what will I be thinking
then about the past so again that
explodes the state space even further
but it allows for like sort of
prospective
retrospective but that that kind of
phenomena is not
here but it's like a modification on
this base
model yeah I guess I was seeing it more
in terms of um the primes and the double
primes on the uh on the bottom set and
maybe that was just my miscorrelation of
just misreading the um terminology as
it's as it's represented for the uh the
lower States so you see I um y y Prime
and then y double Prime
there that's the first derivative and
the second der
right but in order to move back like if
you were if you were collapsing back
into the initial kernel stage wouldn't
it have to still
step through th those premises in that
order or would it all collapse at the
same exact
time again there's a lot to this
question I mean what I'll say is the
role that three plays here the B Matrix
kind of conventionally this is a
transition operator that's describing
how things change from time step to time
time step whereas the three operator in
the continuous setting is describing as
we go to the
right the derivative and as we go to the
left the integral so like you said you
have to walk back through the premises
um step by step from 10 times steps
forward you can go 10 9 8 let's just say
but you can't skip from 10 to
eight at the very least you would need a
different transition operator to apply
backwards similarly um you might be able
to go from X double Prime take the
integral and then take the integral
again but you couldn't take a double
integral in one
jump that wouldn't be the same as these
integrals
okay
but it's kind of like yeah there's other
ways to take it like the computational
irreducibility angle which is like there
might be a shortcut to just apply the
double integral in one step but then
there's also probably equations that you
like can't apply a double
integral and in a way by doing a double
integral in one step you've just made a
single inte you know or by by going two
time steps backwards here you've just
taken one of a different kind of Step
okay yeah because I I ran into something
recently that resolved into a five
integral and that's where I got confused
as to how that was even possible and I'm
still trying to to work through the math
a little bit to
understand but uh that's kind of out of
the scope so I don't want to take too
much time out of
that if you're looking at something
that's that's a really long sequence you
might be able to have statistical power
to talk about like the fifth
derivative but you could simulate
trajectories and then just plot the
first derivative plot the second one
plot and so on and then you'll just find
that maybe there's interesting dynamics
of higher orders or maybe not and then
the empirical way that you could ask
like how important are they would be
okay so we make a real simulation that
has
five um five actual derivatives of
influence and then we make a subset
models that have all five that should be
able to recover 100% of the variance and
then you test the one with four three
two one and there's situations where
even if there's really five the first
derivative covers 99% of it or there
might be ones where the higher
derivatives do
matter okay
thanks
here just just again just to Connected
here's just evaluating the point so to
say you know this is this is like the
true
sea levels for the next 24 hours or this
the real temperature in the room so it's
like if you can only have one number the
best thing you can do is just say what
is the temperature right now and that's
this kind of first approximation and
then if you were to have a second number
you could say okay what's the
temperature in the room and then what's
the the
slope and then if you had another number
you could say okay what's the
temperature right now and the slope and
how fast it's changing and so that
process
is the Taylor series
expansion so that's the kind of way that
they talk about it
in approximating functions because you
can keep on adding more and more
approximating
terms but it can get
unwieldy and you still get and yeah
there's other things to say
but this but I guess I'll just say this
dash line does go off to Infinity like
you could evaluate that dash line at
this point but it' be like way way way
down and then the one of the issues with
using the um Taylor series is you don't
know how good or how bad the dash line
is except by then doing the laborous um
work of checking against the actual
function so like here it's like it
actually is doing really well but it's
not telling you it's doing well you
would just find out by checking but then
over here it's going to be doing
absurdly bad but it's not like it's
going to throw up a yellow flag and tell
you I guess my question in terms of uh
that that dotted line trending to
Infinity is is that assumptive or is
that you know provable in the sense that
we just can't see past a certain State
because it's you know a hidden state or
is it calculable past that hidden state
that is going to be
infinite the dash line is very well
behaved because it's a polom okay it is
this
polom here's the first order polinomial
just a
constant here's the second order it's a
linear yals MX plus b basically MX plus
b
intercept now we're in the quadratic
polom setting so it has all the kind of
simple behavior of
polom which is what makes it a well
behaved approximator for arbitrarily
unruly
functions but it doesn't tell you how
good it
is
okay also just note like on the
pragmatic side pmdp the python active
inference tool kit is only in discreete
time at this point right I'm trying to
translate some of it over too because
I'm starting to work a little bit with
kiss kit or I'm trying to uh to
understand to try and you know use some
of the functions there with Quantum
Gates but that's a little bit beyond um
to try and utilize that as a tool so I'm
trying to put it together a little bit
and then I just got a little bit
confused over the last few days putting
some things together so um I'll keep
looking at it appreciate
oh all
good okay anyone else just unmute and go
for it or feel free to type a question
or we can look at the the upvoted
questions here or any question that was
written in the um chapter six or cohort
six
questions
check okay n
specific
I think it's worth to kind of pull back
a step and look at figure
4.2 figure 4.2 is really helpful because
it kind of builds intuition for what
these base graphs are in terms of like
here's a situation on top left with one
hidden State and one
observable like there's a real
temperature in the room and then there's
a thermometer here's the situation with
one hidden State and two
observables here's a situation with two
contributing factors and one observ
like two things that contribute to a
disease prevalence and here's a chain of
causation so these are like these are
the kinds of things people say
like there was traffic because it was a
sports game and a Friday night it's like
okay that's this
situation or it was a Friday night so
there was a sports game so there was
traffic but those are are the kinds of
things that people talk about when they
use language to describe causal
sequences in the world and then these
variables can be like anything like the
observable could be any modality of
observation and then the hidden States
can be any latent causal Factor
including things that don't like
actually exist in the world like without
arguing too much about whether
temperature actually exists in the world
you can have latent causes that are just
totally
proposed for better and for
worse but this maps onto like a huge
fraction of the kind of statistical
inferences that are
done and this also is kind of like if if
we had like a mind map and we were just
like drawing out causal factors for what
we cared about like this is kind of
intuitively how you would do it like if
one thing was causing multiple
outcomes you draw it like this if
there's multiple things contributing to
cause an observation you could draw it
like
that so this is kind of like where we
touch with more intuitive Notions of
cause and then that is going to get
deployed in this setting where we're
talking about the causal relationships
between
observations hidden States and
actions those are the big players here
and that's being unfolded through
time but those are the things that we
want to connect in our unified model of
perception cognition and action is to a
first
approximation
perception cognition about hidden States
and
action that's why those are like the
major nodes in the white
circles has someone tried to implement
this for like motor
control
yes um motor control has been approached
from the human motor control perspective
like handwriting and movement of the arm
and things like that and also the
robotic motor control setting at the
kind of gross level like where to move
within the warehouse and at the finer
scale like robotic arms and things like
that Dan wasn't that related to what the
Hitachi group
covered I just thought that might be a
good video to point to
yeah good call thanks that was um
guestroom
75 so here was a
robotics in silico so it was not
physical robots it was a simulation of
robots but but this is um a group that's
working with physical robots
and then they
um the visualizations that they show in
the in the Stream were were pretty
interesting and provocative I think in
the sense like it it
[Music]
um it shows how multi-agents and also
how social
norms come into
play so here we have basically the the
red agent is the active inference agent
and then it's going to be like coming on
the opposite direction of the
sidewalk here it's an altruistic other
so the green one has the goal of making
the red one go as little out of the way
as possible whereas the selfish green
one is trying to minimize its
path so those are kind of ways in which
people Implement like even these kind of
social characteristics into to the
preference distributions and the action
Tendencies of different
agents and that's kind of the journey
that chapter six takes us on like which
so that's kind of why the book can be
read in many orders because as it's
written linearly the first five chapters
are like a ton of information that's the
epistemic component and then the second
half of the book starting with chapter
six is like well here's the recipe for
for building the model like what are we
modeling why are we doing it what form
should we use figure 4.3 so just the way
the textbook is written it kind of shows
us a lot of the tools in the workshop
and then we get the recipe in chapter
six but another way to do it and of
course if you go through many times then
it doesn't really matter as much where
you began but another way to to go about
it is start with the system of Interest
Like A system that you're familiar with
or curious about and then start to
reverse engineer like what are the
observations here like who's observing
what I mean I could explore even in this
Starbucks like who's observing what what
are the actions that different agents
are taking what preference distributions
do they have you know some people want
this level of sweetness or this um kind
of coffee
so that's like the kind of low road
approach is starting more with an actual
system and then building up to what
formalisms come into play rather than
like learning all the math
equations and then just hoping that
something like crystallizes out of
nothing thank you Cheryl I'm gonna I'm
gonna bring this in let's look at it
awesome yeah the the these are great
points um like well you know the the
brain is a system of systems so like if
we
up here this could be like this is like
our let's just say this is our portfolio
of
models I mean the brain entertains
multiple causal hypotheses about
events so it is a system of systems and
these are these are yeah good ahead I
guess I meant it's not a system of just
internal systems and that's where I get
um mixed up I mean it's the whole of it
the whole experience in the world we are
not just brains we're in ecosystems
we're in Social systems we're in you
know what I'm saying um
yeah it's like it's such a great and
essential Point that's why we focus so
much on the action perception Loop which
initially seems kind of esoteric but
then we start to see that like all
agents around us are involved in it and
then the only way to account for that
kind of like Dynamic
co-creation with the environment and the
agent is to think about the interface
every time step like if you're on a run
or if you're driving
you can't just focus on well just ignore
the perception for the next time steps
or just ignore the actions for the next
time steps like action and perception
are always happening the agent can't opt
out of those
happening and so it is a joint
entanglement with the
environment and that's like that's
exactly what has to be kind of
modeled to have a holistic model of even
just a rat in a
teamas correct correct so you're right I
like it I like the systems in systems
within systems model but we can only
work with what we can work with that a
time that does infer a certain amount of
reductionism though as if if I
understand it at this level I will
understand it at the
more at the larger level so that's a
that's a an assumption that we bring to
this yeah I again you know there there's
no single order for going through active
inference but figure 9.1 kind of
captures that like here in the center is
the top of figure 4.3 so this is the rat
in the teamas that's the subject of our
study here's the scientists in the lab
so what we choose to present as stimuli
are observations for the rat but they
were choices by us and then the choices
of the Rat become observations for us
and so you could close your analysis
here and say well it's just a rat in a
laboratory or you could model the
building around the
laboratory and you could ask like how
does that context matter and then you
could ask well how confident are we that
the the rat behavior in the lab is like
it is in the
field there's laboratory setups that it
probably transfers and there's ones
where it doesn't but just making the
model of the rap behavior in the lab
does not guarantee
transfer and and that that's why the
system of systems is so
important right okay I love that but I'm
not in chapter nine metab basian
inference oh my gosh I don't even know
I'm gonna get out of chapter four okay
so I'll wait I'll wait there but um I do
I do have a question have you ever heard
of Marilyn Monk who's also at
UCL uh she's a molecular
biologist she has a really interesting
um theory
on uh cause
Consciousness yeah and and um she takes
the systems all the way from Adam to
Cosmos that's what that's what got me uh
thinking about what we're doing here in
this in this book but uh a very
interesting
model that's cool like definitely some
people are going that kind of like
multiscale like down to as small and
fast as you can imagine like Quantum and
then up on through the cosmological and
then this seeing this part here that
reminded me of of a really great book um
evolution in four dimensions which is
like there are genetic epigenetic and
metabolic and cultural and symbolic
inheritances and there situations where
one explains all of the variation but
there's situations where it explains
none so it's not like you can just have
this in principle battle and say oh you
know epigenetics wins or symbolic
variation wins it's like the the field
has been
sketched and then the empirical question
is what matters where and how and then
what but those are questions to address
four specific systems in practice
they're not questions that can be
addressed you know dusted off once and
for all in principle yeah yeah yeah yeah
yeah yeah I mean all right yeah there's
hope for me there's hope for me then
there always
[Laughter]
is it's I mean it's it's fun and it's a
learning there's many things that that
connects because like we're talking
about the systems that we talk about
elsewhere so when we talk about
organisms we're we're we're talking
about the same we're not talking about
some other system and this is more like
a lens that we bring to
systems right a lens we bring the
systems another way to think about that
is like act active inference says less
so we can say
more but it's not like active inference
is g to you know it's not a slot machine
it's not going to deliver us like an
account of a psychiatric or a social
situation I mean the textbook is what it
is like
numbers are just there for people to
count things let's just say so these
models exist for us analyze cognitive
systems but if active inference already
had an answer about how cognitive
systems are right that would that would
curtail it from being used to explore
diverse intelligences and open-endedness
of creating new
things
yeah got
it and that's why like yeah thank you
that's why chapter four gives us the
like the generative
model it's like this is like the Linux
current or like the software system but
it's like but what do I do with a
computer it's like well chapter 5 here's
people using it to study
Nels but in chapter four we see it in
kind of its pure
form in the general or in the abstract
form which is like both sometimes very
frustrating or it feels like it's like a
mega infinite Learning Journey but all
of the connection from ACM to any system
we make that connection that connection
is not for us to
find
Dan could you uh go back really quick
for me to uh the chapter was I scroll
down I think it was five where you had
gone down to uh Consciousness related to
that um we introduced um the
differential between animal and uh
trees this quote here or plants yes
sorry
um so in terms of they have no brain so
they're called plants but in the in the
context of the tree itself isn't that
wouldn't that be considered
um in the same way that Cheryl was just
talking about different layers of the
brain where the tree structure itself
right has its own branches and nodes
that are still connected in the same
field that may grow around but again
you're also deal dealing with different
Dynamics where those systems will still
interact given how close they are for
Fitness of reaching the sun you know
variably if another Leaf is over another
leaf for
example I totally agree like it's kind
of a um it's the kind of quote that a
mammal
said
like I think about this
paper this is my PhD adviser and a
colleague a framework for plant behavior
and I mean now this is more of a common
perspective but um there is some
question whether the words to describe
animal behavior such as the word
Behavior or foraging can be applied to
the activities of plant I mean is a root
tip not foraging for nutrients in a
niche oh it's slow okay but not to
itself it's slow to a person running
around but
um so oh clant don't have Behavior
they're just there but they do have
behavior and then active inference helps
us say yeah here's the affordances they
have and the time skills over which they
have them but you couldn't say like
something you know doesn't have Behavior
just because it doesn't have a kind of
behavior
right well
that go ahead go ahead sorry go ahead no
go ahead Char sorry
I I was just saying that um Behavior Uh
assumes
Consciousness and Oxford dictionary
defines it as the state of being aware
and responsive to one's surroundings so
if you like Marilyn monk she talks about
awareness is sensing so if we say
sensing and responsive to one
surrounding then we have to say plants
have a Consciousness according to Oxford
dictionary so what you're what you're
saying saying about the leaf and the
tree and the root
tip um brings the word Consciousness
here which is problematic for me because
it has no end I mean what doesn't sense
and
respond so I guess say even rocks do
that that's that's these are the mega
philosophical questions like does pan
cognitivism the idea like we approach
all things as cognitive systems or that
they truly are cognitive systems does
pan cognitivism imply pan
psychism is there something it's like to
be anything because all things are
engaged across the interface in sensing
and adapting even something that's inert
it's still is bounded by an interface
and there's still something on the other
side of the interface even if it's just
a cup of water but then is there
something it's like to be a cup of water
because it'd be different if the cup of
water weren't there so it's doing
something in relationship to its
Niche and so that's people looking for
continuums where it looks like there's
sharp distinctions and looking for Sharp
distinctions amidst the continua like it
has to have a higher order awareness
like it has to be aware that it's
aware like our attention is not only
about Target of our attention we're also
aware that we're paying attention to
something and this is where so many of
the people bring in like
meditation and the mindfulness
connections and then some people use
that to differentiate or distinguish
human cognition from other types other
people deploy like literally the same
formalisms to argue for the continuity
of human
cognition
and then this has been oh yeah go ahead
um has there been discussion around like
how much our
sensors um contribute to our cognitive
function say I mean just just as a mind
experiment you if you took a human brain
and you put into a dog's body would we
start thinking like a dog
more
like people have thought wild
stuff well I mean just to come at that
from a different perspective I was
thinking about this the other day in
terms of cybernetics right like if we
get to a point where we're able to do a
full transplant of you know a mind for
example into a cybernetic system
wouldn't that be the same argument you
know would would you have the same kind
of organ rejection for example um but it
would would it
be and I guess that would be very
assumptive at this point but like would
the the false body reject the mind or
would the Mind reject the false body in
that
sense I was thinking of more from this
perspective of you know how necessary is
it for intelligence or like general
intelligence like you know do want if
want to get high level's intelligence do
we need a an embodiment system that
you know senses the
world um in in a complex way that you we
have you I think we have
like uh 100,000 like Sten receptors or
something our body and it's continuously
feeding into our body for many different
layers and you know maybe that's
something that that's crucial to you
know the feelings and emotions that we
have um you because there theories where
you know like our our stomach itself
contributes to our you know cognitive
function
so you know I wonder there's been
discussion there from you kist and or in
the active influence Community because
the um you
know this community seems to think more
about um I think the
holistic
um yeah just a bigger picture in terms
of
intelligence so I did my PhD at the
University of Virginia in the United
States and there was a little known
secret there of a guy who studied
near-death experiences reincarnation
from all over the world Ian Stevenson
was his name uh they didn't even really
talk about him until years and years
decades later um he was a well-known
secret but his point was that uh
Consciousness can exist without a body
and even without a
brain and at that time it really got me
yeah there he is uh it really got me to
thinking about this whole idea of Truth
um there is a scientific model of Truth
in which of course this is done by
humans but before there were scientists
there were still people seeking truth
and even in Act of inference they're
called the
mystics um and then I think in our day
you know there there are poets who kind
of intuitively or think deeply about
something but it's still a search for
truth so I think um for me it has been
useful to acknowledge these different
ways and perspectives and
modalities and not think one is greater
than the
other that's a great Point there's so
much to say it it reminds me of like
there's the parable of the the blind
people and the elephants and they're
like touching different parts of the
elephants okay now we could kind of
modify that into one person can see one
can hear one can smell one can talk so
there's different modalities that have
not just touching a different part of
the body but they're actually getting
like a different wavelength they're
getting totally different modalities of
the
elephants um that's that's one
interesting component and then one other
point is like um so earlier asked like
what is the role of the sensation and
perception in intelligence
there's a ton of answers but one answer
that like Adam saffron and others have
pursued is um the kinds of relationships
that our sensory
apparatus require to
solve help us build architectures that
reflect the structure of our reality
like grid cells in the brain those
evolved because we were moving in spaces
with certain geometries
but then those became later utilized for
other kinds of arbitrary cognitive
navigation or like having hierarchically
nested perceptual
apparatus it arose to
do something that it was repurposed to
do later because that Motif is so
effective at the kind of statistical
challenge that it evolved to solve or
address and there's probably no end to
those
motifs
wow yeah it's super it's like chapter
four is so hard this is where it has to
take
us can I I know over time can can I ask
like a very fine Grand question to zoom
all the way back in yeah yeah um so I I
kept getting confused in the text by
some of the conventions in the math um
are bold faces and our serifs versus S
serifs meant to mean anything so if you
look at equation 4.11 for example we
have caps SF f equals bold pi times bold
SF F and I I I looked around I couldn't
figure out like what if anything are
those like changes in the specifics of
how things are rendered meant to
indicate
I'm totally with you that's one reason
why like having the um having the
written equation
form I feel like is really vital because
even even experts will
not be able to converge upon this kind
of a
description without looking at the same
page there's just too many ways to read
even the equations and that's even
before you get into like bold and
italics and like font and stuff like
that
[Music]
um it looks like bold is only mentioned
one time in the supplement or appendix
B referring to it as being like a
sufficient statistic but I don't think
that's how it's being used above I feel
like bold is being used to describe
whether it's a vector or
not but
I I I don't know and like faced with
that daunting of trying to sift through
where they or if they Define
it for like typographical phenomena that
I don't even necessarily know the name
of that's why I'm very excited for
ontology driven natural language
descriptions of the equations and then
we can render them to look however we
want so we could render them with a full
English word or we could render it with
a full non-english word or we could use
a python
variable because I I don't even if you
could dig to the bottom and find out if
they defined how they use
notation other papers are going to do
different notation so it'd be kind of
like a a local
victory yeah at this point I would be
satis or I would be helped by local
Victory there's like a couple of pages
where they like seem to use this
distinction a lot and I was like not
following their choices at all um but
but yeah I appreciate that like a shared
resource like helps create some clarity
um but uh
yeah okay equation
411 uh yeah is an example and then like
above and below this there's a few
there's like a number of others that are
uh I think in to use the same
distinction and I I have to assume that
the authors had some purpose in
mind so I don't think it's just like
Matrix versus Vector versus
scalar
and the question is what does the Bold
typing versus the italics mean what does
what does the bold mean and what does
the serif versus un serif
mean
okay and if if no one knows I guess no
one knows and that that's the state of
the world but yeah I was I was what do
you mean by S you mean this F versus
this F right so they are distinguished
by by the Bold feature but like other
things are are also distinguished by the
Bold feature but not by the SF versus SF
change okay it seems like we always have
a co-occurrence of
bold and
straight and italics is never found as
bold
so I'm tempted to say that bold and
straight means sufficient statistics
of whereas the italics is referring to
the underlying variable as it is but we
can like literally just write the
question down in one of the rows and
then whatever we can't resolve we can
email friston at all okay fair enough
thanks
yeah
yeah yeah I
mean I dream of the day when we can
Mouse
over and have multiple modalities of
what these are and and like have someone
says I want to Mouse over and see
examples someone else says I want to
Mouse over and see like the programming
variable I I don't know if there's
another way to make like a fixed
artifact that that
could speak to so many people in so many
different
situations okay all right
well interesting times question uh yeah
yeah um I then coding exercises that I
can go for to um understand these um
equations
better yes i' go go over the code page
here's several dozen um code uh examples
like when you see and then also I would
highly recommend the PDP
documentation because like when it's
shown as the base graph and it's like it
seems like again it seems like it's
going to be like this math and
analytical thing but when you go to
active inference from
scratch you you define
ABCD and then you have all of the
steps all of the utility functions are
are
defined and then um you have the active
inference
Loop and then once you've gotten to here
here's active inference Loop A B C D and
the environment and the time
Horizon so if you've um run up at the
equations Andor you want to try a little
bit more of like a bottomup computer
science or computer engineering
approach this can be really
clarifying but those are very useful
with
PDP um but any of the code examples will
be fun or useful however pmdp and RX and
fur H um have the best
documentation so and we're here to make
the the material more pedagogical so if
there's like a example that you're
excited about like Lally let's have the
authors do a live stream or let's make
the code better annotated or documented
or whatever we need to
do um do they have any examples where
they're doing um active influence on
just some
basic um basic
predictions like I don't know tempature
or yes like um
the uh RX
infer
documentation has has like a range of
examples um ranging from
like
like don't worry about something being
too simple truly like even the
examples um
of coin flipping are a great place to
start but this is a ton of information
about all kinds of examples and
then usually the people who are making
the packages are focused on making the
package if not like working three jobs
so if something's missing I mean change
the world or change your mind so if you
think there could be a cool
example that's what we're doing here so
I hope that we can make it if it's not
already
there yeah wow that was chapter
4 the next two weeks we'll come back for
chapter five and look at more examples
in the Maman nervous
system and then we'll have just a final
meeting kind of catch
up hopefully get people's feedback and
connect on projects and just see where
things are at in The Institute the
ecosystem so thank you all see you next
time thank you bye bye thanks everyone
thank you